<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A learned and fruitfull sermon preached in Christs Church in Norwich. By Mr. Nevvhouse, late preacher of Gods word there.</title>
            <author>Newhouse, Thomas, d. 1611.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08130</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18494</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100052</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99835905</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99835905</idno>
            <idno type="VID">137</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08130)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 137)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1282:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A learned and fruitfull sermon preached in Christs Church in Norwich. By Mr. Nevvhouse, late preacher of Gods word there.</title>
                  <author>Newhouse, Thomas, d. 1611.</author>
                  <author>Hill, Robert, d. 1623.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[56] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by T. Snodham] for Ionas Man, and are to be solde at the signe of the Talbot in Paternoster-row,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: pi A-E.</note>
                  <note>Editor's preface signed: Robert Hill.</note>
                  <note>Pi2 missigned A.</note>
                  <note>Includes, at end, "A right godly prayer, made by Mr. Newhouse".</note>
                  <note>Caption title: A sermon preached at great S. Maries, in Cambridge.</note>
                  <note>Some pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:137:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:137:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LEARNED AND FRVIT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FVLL SERMON, Preached in Chriſts Church in Norwich.</p>
            <p>BY M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. NEVVHOVSE, late Preacher of Gods Word there.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 PETER 3.18.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>For Chriſt alſo hath once ſuffered for ſinnes, the iuſt for the vniuſt, that he might bring vs to God.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON: Printed for <hi>Ionas Man,</hi> and are to be ſolde at the ſigne of the Talbot in Paternoſter-row. 1612.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:137:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:137:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Thomas Layer,</hi> an ancient Senator, and a iuſt Iuſtice of Peace, in the Citie of Norwich: Grace and Peace.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT Worſhipfull, though the <hi>Word</hi> of God be the <hi>Bread</hi> of life, yet the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of Gods word are his <hi>Stewards</hi> to deuide it: and though the ſame <hi>Word</hi> be the <hi>Water</hi> of Life, yet they are his <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duits</hi> to conuey it. If the <hi>Bread</hi> in a loafe be not <hi>cut</hi> out vnto the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry,
<pb facs="tcp:137:3"/> an <hi>Infant</hi> that is hungry may dye with a whole loafe in his hands: and if the <hi>Water</hi> in a fountaine be not <hi>drawne</hi> out to the thirſty, a <hi>childe</hi> may periſh with a bottle in his armes.</p>
            <p>How neceſſary it is, that the <hi>one</hi> ſhould be cut out to the hungry ſoule, and the <hi>other</hi> drawne out to the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie ſpirit, they know beſt that haue the care of their owne family, and how neceſſary it is that both the <hi>bread</hi> and <hi>water</hi> of life, ſhould be <hi>carued</hi> and <hi>fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> out to all ſuch as <hi>hunger</hi> and <hi>thirſt</hi> after righteouſneſſe, they know well who haue any care of Gods <hi>Family.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We that liue in this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> haue good experience of Gods fauour towards vs in this reſpect. We haue many a faithfull <hi>Ahimelech</hi> amongst vs, who rather then <hi>Dauid</hi> ſhould pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh for hunger, will giue vnto him the <hi>Shew-bread</hi> of the Sanctuary: We
<pb facs="tcp:137:3"/> haue many a <hi>worthy Miniſter</hi> amongſt vs, who rather then <hi>Dauid</hi> ſhould dye for thirſt, will with the hazard of their liues giue vnto him of the <hi>waters</hi> of <hi>Bethlehem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When I enter into a ſerious medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Maieſtie</hi> of Gods Word, and withall conſider that <hi>all</hi> is as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing without application, methinkes I doe ſay, here is <hi>ſalue:</hi> but where is the <hi>hand</hi> that must lay it on the <hi>ſoare?</hi> Here is <hi>Balme:</hi> where is the <hi>finger</hi> that muſt poure it into the wound? Here is <hi>Phyſicke:</hi> where is the <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian?</hi> And here is the <hi>Poole</hi> of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſdah:</hi> where is the <hi>friend</hi> that will help vs in? Doe we looke for an <hi>hand?</hi> the hand of <hi>Gods Miniſter</hi> will lay on the <hi>ſalue.</hi> Doe we deſire a <hi>finger?</hi> The finger of <hi>Gods Miniſter</hi> will poure in this <hi>oyle.</hi> Would we ſend for a <hi>Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian?</hi> the Art of <hi>Gods Miniſter</hi> will adminiſter this <hi>Phyſicke.</hi> And if at
<pb facs="tcp:137:4"/> the deſcent of the Angell, we would faine be put into the <hi>Poole</hi> of <hi>Betheſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> who will ſooner doe it then this <hi>Man of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot deny, but that by reading of Gods word a man may <hi>receiue</hi> much comfort: nay, I am perſwaded that by the ſame, he may be excellently <hi>prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> to get ſauing knowledge: yet <hi>prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching</hi> is that <hi>alone</hi> ordinary meanes, which God hath <hi>ſanctified</hi> for the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of his Children, and to make them <hi>wiſe</hi> vnto that ſaluation.</p>
            <p>By preaching, the <hi>Minde</hi> of the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant is <hi>enlightned:</hi> the <hi>Memorie</hi> of the forgetfull is <hi>ſtrengthened:</hi> the <hi>Heart</hi> of the obſtinate is <hi>mollified:</hi> the <hi>Affections</hi> of the vntoward are <hi>reduced:</hi> the <hi>Will</hi> of the peruerſe is <hi>reſtrained:</hi> and the <hi>Life</hi> of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly ſo <hi>changed,</hi> that at the voyce of a ſimple and ſinfull man, he cryeth out with the Iewes in the <hi>Acts, Men and
<pb facs="tcp:137:4"/> brethren, what ſhall I doe to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued?</hi> This made <hi>Dauid</hi> to ſay, <hi>I am the man: Saul</hi> to ſay, <hi>I haue ſinned:</hi> and euery priuate <hi>conuert</hi> to ſay: <hi>God is in theſe men indeed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Were it not for <hi>preaching</hi> of the Word, where were the <hi>vnderſtanding</hi> of it? where were the <hi>conſolation</hi> by it? where were <hi>direction</hi> from it? Without it how ſhould <hi>hard</hi> places be made <hi>plaine?</hi> plaine be <hi>applyed?</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnances in it be <hi>reconciled?</hi> or op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugners of it be <hi>confuted?</hi> Take away <hi>Preaching,</hi> and then downe with our <hi>Schooles</hi> of learning, our <hi>Houſes</hi> of prayer, our <hi>Obedience</hi> to Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, our <hi>Loue</hi> to equals, and our <hi>right</hi> to heauen.</p>
            <p>I am now in a <hi>Labirinth,</hi> I cannot well come out. The <hi>Preaching</hi> of the Goſpell, is the <hi>power</hi> of God vnto <hi>ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation:</hi> the <hi>Pillar</hi> of God in our iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to <hi>Canaan:</hi> the <hi>Angell</hi> of God
<pb facs="tcp:137:5"/> to bring vs out of <hi>Sodome:</hi> the <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger</hi> of God to prepare <hi>his way:</hi> the <hi>Trumpet</hi> of God, to cry downe <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>richo:</hi> and the <hi>Hammer</hi> of God to driue in the <hi>nayle</hi> of piety, and to breake out the <hi>braines</hi> of profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>How much we are beholding to the <hi>Preachers</hi> of the Goſpell we ſhall then know, when the Lord ſhall ſend ſuch a <hi>Famine</hi> of this <hi>Bread,</hi> that though we goe from East to Weſt we ſhall not finde it: or ſuch a <hi>Drought</hi> of this <hi>water</hi> of life, that we ſhall runne from Citie to Citie, and ſhall not get it. But bleſſed be God, we are now full: and I wiſh it may neuer be ſaid vnto vs, <hi>Woe be vnto you that are full.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Amongst many Cities in this <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Kingdome,</hi> beholding vnto God for the Miniſtery of the Word, you in your Citie are not the leaſt beholding. Euery <hi>Sabbath</hi> day, in many of your
<pb facs="tcp:137:5"/> 
               <hi>Churches</hi> is the Word <hi>preached,</hi> and almoſt <hi>euery day</hi> in the weeke, the preaching of the ſame is painfully <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſurely, when I conſider the <hi>paines</hi> required of your Citie preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, the vncertaine <hi>allowance</hi> proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for them, the <hi>meane eſtate</hi> they muſt euer needs liue in, and that <hi>ſound Learning</hi> which hath beene, and is now in many of them, I beginne to thinke, that it is eyther the <hi>ſweete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of the ayre, or the <hi>ciuilitie</hi> of your people, or the <hi>contentedneſſe</hi> of their mindes, or their <hi>deſire</hi> to doe good, or the <hi>ſpecial bleſſing</hi> of almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, that continues thus amongst you the <hi>great</hi> meanes of ſaluation.</p>
            <p>But howſoeuer the <hi>Arke</hi> of Gods Couenant be beautifully ſet vp in your ſeuerall Temples, yet to you of S. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drewes</hi> hath God appeared in <hi>excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> beauty. How many <hi>hungry</hi> ſoules
<pb facs="tcp:137:6"/> in that Citie are almoſt daily <hi>fed</hi> at your table? How many <hi>thirſtie</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits doe drinke ordinarily of your Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternes? And I doubt whether any one Pariſh in the Kingdome hath been ſo ſucceſsiuely bleſſed with learned and laborious Miniſters, as you haue beene, for almoſt threeſcore yeeres.</p>
            <p>If you forget that <hi>faithfull</hi> Seruant of Chriſt <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. More,</hi> who for twentie yeeres together preached amongst you almoſt <hi>euery</hi> day in the weeke, beſides his <hi>priuate</hi> conferences in your ſeuerall families, ſurely then I feare me there is a ſtate riſen vp amongst you, like vnto that of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> whoſe <hi>King</hi> knew not <hi>Ioſeph.</hi> But I know you remember both him and his.</p>
            <p>And can you then forget this wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy man, who for the ſpace of <hi>foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene</hi> yeeres paſt, liued partly a <hi>Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher,</hi> and partly a <hi>Paſtor</hi> in your <hi>Congregation?</hi> Concerning whom I
<pb facs="tcp:137:6"/> might ſay much (and if a learned <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> doth not deceiue me, <hi>it is pietie to commend the dead,</hi>) but I muſt not make an <hi>Epiſtle</hi> larger then the booke. I <hi>liued</hi> with him in a famous <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> I <hi>laboured</hi> with him in your holy <hi>Citie,</hi> for the ſpace of fiue yeeres and more: and I euer obſerued him <hi>diligent</hi> in his ſtudie: <hi>wittie</hi> in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, <hi>apprehenſiue</hi> of truth, <hi>deepe</hi> in knowledge, <hi>powerfull</hi> in preaching, <hi>vigilant</hi> in practiſing, and a <hi>perfect patterne</hi> of grauitie and ſobrietie in the whole courſe of his life and conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation. And if the ſpirit of that iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Perkins</hi> might be found in any Diuine, I thinke it appeared in him.</p>
            <p>It is the <hi>Art of Arts</hi> to preach well, to <hi>diuide</hi> the word, and to <hi>ſaue</hi> ſoules: hee excelled in this <hi>Art:</hi> and that he might grow in this knowledge, he tooke ſuch paines, that like vnto a
<pb facs="tcp:137:7"/> 
               <hi>ſeruiceable candle,</hi> in giuing <hi>light</hi> to you, he <hi>conſumed</hi> himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Though there be too many <hi>Bookes</hi> in this <hi>ſcribling</hi> age, and the <hi>paper</hi> is worth more then the <hi>things</hi> that are written in them, (as <hi>Socrates</hi> once ſaid, when he would write nothing) yet of ſome mens <hi>Labours</hi> there are too few. For though they ſhould write but that which <hi>before</hi> hath beene written, yet by reaſon of their <hi>credit</hi> in the Church, the <hi>ſoundneſſe</hi> of their iudgement, the <hi>vprightneſſe</hi> of their life, their <hi>experience</hi> in caſes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie and conſcience, and that <hi>loue</hi> which their auditors haue had to them and their doctrine, they might by wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting doe much good.</p>
            <p>Wee reade not indeede that our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt</hi> committed of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe any thing to writing: yet his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> hee made as his <hi>Hand</hi> and <hi>Secretaries,</hi> to commend the
<pb facs="tcp:137:7"/> 
               <hi>New Teſtament</hi> to the Church of God.</p>
            <p>Our aduerſaries the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> daily doe aſſault the Church with <hi>deadly</hi> weapons; the poyſon of <hi>Aſpes</hi> is vnder their pennes: if theſe <hi>Fooles</hi> were not anſwered to their <hi>Folly,</hi> they would be too proud.</p>
            <p>Our Aduerſary the <hi>Diuell</hi> caſteth daily new <hi>deuiſed</hi> darts into the minds and Conſciences of people: if he ſhould not be <hi>reſiſted</hi> by the Sling of <hi>Dauid,</hi> hee would ſoone <hi>triumph</hi> ouer the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael of God.</p>
            <p>True it is indeede, that by the <hi>mouth</hi> of the Preacher wee receiue much good, and the <hi>liuely</hi> voyce giues much <hi>life</hi> to diſcourſe: but when, after hearing, wee may with our <hi>eyes peruſe</hi> that which our eare hath heard, wee ſhall the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>ponder,</hi> and <hi>know,</hi> and <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> and <hi>affect</hi> that which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb facs="tcp:137:8"/> we might vtterly forget: and make our hearts as rich in grace, as our Bookes are full of goodneſſe.</p>
            <p>To this end, that which was preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto the <hi>eare,</hi> in the aſſembly of many <hi>learned Diuines,</hi> and by name, before that Reuerend <hi>Doctor Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> late <hi>Biſhop</hi> of your Dioceſſe, I am bold to publiſh to your <hi>view:</hi> that by the finger of this <hi>Herculean</hi> labourer, you may know what the whole man was.</p>
            <p>And the ſame I am bold to dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate to your <hi>Worſhip,</hi> as a teſtimonie of your long loue to me, and my deſire to be thankfull to you.</p>
            <p>When I liued in your <hi>Pariſh</hi> a pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Preacher, I found <hi>ſeeming</hi> fauor at the hands of ſome <hi>curious,</hi> but <hi>ſubſtantiall</hi> fauour of diuers <hi>courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> and <hi>true</hi> meaning people.</p>
            <p>How in the firſt yeere of my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, I was entertained by that graue
<pb facs="tcp:137:8"/> Senator, <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Francis Rugge,</hi> then the third time <hi>Maior</hi> of that happy Citie, I <hi>cannot</hi> forget, whoſe houſe was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me rather an <hi>habitation</hi> then an <hi>Inne:</hi> How euer after I was welcome to you, and continually was fed at your table, I <hi>muſt not</hi> forget, vnleſſe I would be thought an vnthankfull man.</p>
            <p>I acknowledge all with much thanks, both to <hi>God,</hi> for ſuch a <hi>friend,</hi> and to <hi>you</hi> for ſuch <hi>friendſhip:</hi> and deſire that when both you and I ſhall haue gone the way of all fleſh, the kindneſſe which you haue ſhewed to me, may (of all into whoſe hands this little Booke ſhall come) he had in remembrance.</p>
            <p>I am now at an end. I preſent vnto you this learned <hi>Sermon</hi> of the <hi>Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication</hi> of a ſinner before God, with an excellent <hi>Prayer</hi> which <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. New-houſe</hi> gaue me, written with his owne hand. I doubt not of your kinde accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb facs="tcp:137:9"/> of them both: and I truſt they will be a welcome New-yeeres gift to the whole Citie, who I hope will euer <hi>obey them that haue the ouer-ſight of them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 13.</note> 
               <hi>and ſubmit themſelues to them: for they watch for their ſoules, euen as they that muſt giue accounts: that they may doe it with ioy and not with griefe: for that is vnprofitable for them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I pray, that as the true <hi>feare</hi> of God hath ſo encreaſed your happy dayes vpon earth, that you haue attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the age of <hi>foureſcore</hi> yeeres, and for aboue <hi>fortie</hi> yeeres paſt haue liued a worthy <hi>Senator</hi> of a moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <hi>Citie;</hi> ſo it would pleaſe God, when your <hi>glaſſe</hi> is <hi>runne,</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> ſhall call for <hi>you,</hi> you may with old <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon depart</hi> in peace; with faithfull <hi>Samuel</hi> be <hi>lamented</hi> for, and after receiue <hi>the end of your Faith, which is the ſaluation of your Soule.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:137:9"/>
            <p>Thus crauing pardon, recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>you,</hi> your vertuous Wife M<hi rend="sup">ris.</hi> 
               <hi>Anne Layer,</hi> with that bountifull and godly Widdow M<hi rend="sup">ris.</hi> 
               <hi>Anne Rugge,</hi> to the protection of the Almighty, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly take my leaue.</p>
            <p>From <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Andrew Curwaynes</hi> houſe in <hi>Salisburie-rents,</hi> at S. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins</hi> in the Fields. <hi>Decemb. 3. 1611.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips euer in the Lord, ROBERT HILL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:137:10"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:137:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED AT Great S. <hi>Maries,</hi> in Cambridge.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 COR. 5.21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For he made him which knew no ſinne, to be ſinne for vs; that we ſhould be made the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of God in him.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Rom the ninth verſe of this Chapter to the eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth, the Apoſtle com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth his faithfulneſſe and ſinceritie in the execution of his function Apoſtolicall. From the eighteenth verſe vnto the end, hee
<pb facs="tcp:137:11"/> commendeth the doctrine of the Goſpell, and that by a double argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: the former whereof is taken from the Authour or efficient cauſe, who is, GOD himſelfe: the latter from the effect, to wit, reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betweene God and man; and therefore it is called the Miniſterie of reconciliation. Further this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect is enlarged by ſundry argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: firſt, from the Authour, who is alſo God himſelfe: ſecondly, from the ſubiect, <hi>viz.</hi> the World, by a Metonimie of the ſubiect, men li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in the world; and by a Synec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doche of the whole for the part, the Elect in the world: thirdly, from the forme, <hi>viz.</hi> the not imputing of ſinne: fourthly, from the adiuuant cauſes, that is, the Miniſters of the word, to whom the diſpenſation of this heauenly ambaſſage is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, verſe 19. and 20. fiftly, from
<pb facs="tcp:137:11"/> the meritorious &amp; impulſiue cauſe, which is the worke of Chriſts Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatorſhippe, in vndertaking the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of mans ſinne before God. verſe 21.</p>
            <p>Wherein three things more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly are to be conſidered. Firſt, our Sauiour Chriſt, the Redeemer and reconciler of the world, is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by his adioynt or propertie, which is puritie of nature, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitie from ſinne, in theſe words, <hi>(Which knew no ſinne.)</hi> Secondly, his worke is propounded, whereby hee merited and procured at the hands of his Father, attonement and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation between God and man, in theſe words, (<hi>became ſinne for vs.</hi> Thirdly, this work is amplified from the vſe and end of it, which is the iuſtification of a ſinner before God, in the laſt words, <hi>(that we might be made the righteouſneſſe of GOD in
<pb facs="tcp:137:12"/> him.)</hi> Thus much ſhall ſuffice to haue ſpoken of the coherence, order, and reſolution of theſe wordes.</p>
            <p>Now to deſcend to a more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular examination of them, let vs firſt of all ſearch the true and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per meaning of the wordes, and then proceede to the vſe of doctrine and edification which they ſhall na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally afford.</p>
            <p>Firſt, therefore whereas the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith, <hi>he made him,</hi> the meaning is, God the Father in his eternall and vnchangeable counſell, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed and appointed him which knew no ſinne to become ſinne for vs, and anſwerably, in fulneſſe of time, ſent his Sonne to take vpon him fleſh, that is, mans nature, that in the ſame he might worke and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer whatſoeuer was to be done and ſuffered for the accompliſhment of mans redemption. This appeareth to
<pb facs="tcp:137:12"/> be ſo, both becauſe the outward and external works of God ſtretch them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues not onely to the diuels them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, but to the executions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as alſo becauſe this worke of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption and Reconciliation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and man, as it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun in the decree of God, ſo it was continued in the incarnation of Chriſt, and then finiſhed and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed when all our ſinne and guilt was laid vpon him, and he paid the ranſome for them all.</p>
            <p>And leaſt this ſhould ſeeme ſtrange and hard to any, that Chriſt being very God ſhould be any way ſubiect or ſubordinate vnto the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of God, the Scripture is plaine and pregnant in this point: 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20. <hi>He was fore-appointed, or fore-or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained from the beginning of the world, viz.</hi> to this worke of media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And our Sauiour Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:137:13"/> ſpeaketh plainely, <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.27. <hi>Him hath the Father ſealed,</hi> that is, ſigned and ſingled, by ſetting as it were, a ſtamp and marke vpon him, thereby ſeparating him vnto this worke.</p>
            <p>This we ſhall the better conceiue if wee doe but remember this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction: Chriſt is to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of vs two wayes: firſt, abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as he is God, in which reſpect be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing equall with the Father and the holy Ghoſt, he decreeth &amp; determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth together with them all things that are or come to paſſe in heauen or in earth: ſecondly, with limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or addition, <hi>viz.</hi> as hee is God incarnate, God manifeſted in the fleſh, the mediator and reconciler of the world; in which reſpect hee may be truly ſaid to be vnder the decree of God, though not in reſpect of his Nature, yet in reſpect of his Office.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:137:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Which knew no ſin.</hi>] The meaning is not that our Sauiour Chriſt was ignorant of the nature, qualitie and force of ſinne, all our ſinnes being laid vpon him, but he knew no ſin, to wit, experimentally, eyther inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in his perſon or practiſed in his life; in a word, he was no ſinner at al, eyther by the guilt of <hi>Adams</hi> firſt tranſgreſſion, or by the corruption of nature proceeding thence, or by any actual offence committed in all his life. The Scripture is cleere and euident in this point: And firſt for original ſin, that is the guilt and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of nature, <hi>Lu.</hi> 1.35. The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell <hi>Gabriel</hi> in his ſalutation to the Virgine <hi>Marie,</hi> ſaith, that that which ſhall be borne of her, ſhall be holy, that is, pure and free from all ſtaine and contagion of originall ſinne: <hi>Hebre.</hi> 4.15. <hi>Hee was tempted in all things like vnto vs, yet without ſinne.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:137:14"/> And though this were a ſufficient reaſon to exempt our Sauiour Chriſt from all actuall ſinne, yet the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is not wanting in this point alſo, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.46. he cleareth himſelfe from all actuall tranſgreſſion, when hee ſaith, <hi>Which of you can</hi> conuince or <hi>rebuke me of ſinne?</hi> And for them both, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. Chriſt ſuffered, the iuſt for the vniuſt, iuſt in nature, iuſt in actions. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.26 <hi>Such an high Prieſt it became vs to haue, as is holy, vndefiled, innocent, and ſeparate from ſinners.</hi> And the reaſon is ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred in the wordes following, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee muſt not be like to the high Prieſts of the Law, who being ſinners themſelues, firſt offered ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for themſelues, and then for the people; but hee muſt be an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute and perfect high Prieſt, that he may be in all points an abſolute and a perfect Sauiour.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:137:14"/>
            <p>The ground of all this is, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie and miraculous ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of our Sauiour Chriſt in the womb of the Virgin, wherof there be two parts: the firſt is the ſtay &amp; ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page of the guilt of <hi>Adams</hi> firſt tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, with the corruption of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture proceeding thence, which was done on this manner: God in the beginning tooke this order touching man, that whatſoeuer good he had, he ſhould haue it for himſelf and his poſteritie, and whatſoeuer euill or hurt he brought vpon himſelfe, that hee ſhould deriue it to euery one of his poſterity deſcending from him, inſomuch as euery father is in ſtead of <hi>Adam,</hi> to conuey vnto his childe not onely nature and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but the guilt alſo and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of nature: now that this euill might be preuented in Chriſt, God in great wiſdome appointed that he
<pb facs="tcp:137:15"/> ſhould be immediately conceiued by the holy Ghoſt in the wombe of the Virgin, without any manner ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration by man, inſomuch as hee tooke ſubſtance from <hi>Marie</hi> without the guilt and corruption of nature.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiect.</hi> If it ſhall be obiected (as the ſpirit of errour hath found one only cauill againſt this cleere truth) that all that are in <hi>Adam</hi> haue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in him but our Sauiour Chriſt was in <hi>Adam, ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> The propoſition is not true, vnleſſe it be thus expounded: All that are in <hi>Adam</hi> haue ſinned in him, ſobeit they deſcend from him by ordinary generation. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. the holy Ghoſt ſaith, <hi>by one man ſinne entered into the world,</hi> he doth not ſay from one man, ſignifying that <hi>Adam</hi> conueyeth the corruption of nature to no more then he doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get: for the Aſſumption, it muſt be
<pb facs="tcp:137:15"/> diſtinguiſhed; our Sauiour Chriſt was in <hi>Adam</hi> not ſimply as other men are, but in part onely, that is, in regard of ſubſtance which hee tooke from <hi>Adam,</hi> but not in regard of the propagation of nature by ordinarie generation. All other men are from <hi>Adam,</hi> and by <hi>Adam;</hi> but hee is from him onely, and not by him, as by a begetter and procreant cauſe.</p>
            <p>The ſecond part is the infuſion of holineſſe into the manhoode of Chriſt, ſo farre forth as is meet for the perſon and office of a Mediator.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Became ſinne for vs.</hi>] Theſe words at the firſt ſight may ſeeme to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply a contradiction, but being right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expounded, all difficultie will ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be remoued. Some expound <hi>(Sinne)</hi> a ſacrifice for ſinne, by a Metonimie of the ſubiect, Sinne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the obiect of ſacrifice, ſpecially of the propitiatory ſacrifice, which
<pb facs="tcp:137:16"/> was conuerſant about the expiation of ſinne: this expoſition is Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxe, agreeable to the Analogie of Faith, the tenure of Scripture, and the vſe of the word, which often in the Scripture admitteth this trope, as might be ſhewed in many places of the old Teſtament if neede were. Neuertheleſſe it ſeemeth not to be ſo fit and ſutable vnto this place, &amp; that for two reaſons principally: firſt, becauſe of the Antitheſis here vſed by the Apoſtle, wherein if by one member, <hi>viz. Sinne,</hi> wee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand a ſacrifice for ſinne and no more, ſo as our guilt and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall be tranſlated vnto Chriſt alone, and not the fault (as <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> and the Rhemiſts would haue it) then neceſſarily by righteouſneſſe in the ſecond member wee muſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the reward and fruit of righteouſneſſe, which cannot ſtand;
<pb facs="tcp:137:16"/> becauſe the very righteouſneſſe it ſelfe is imputed to iuſtification, as afterward we ſhall ſhew. Secondly, it is vnequall and vniuſt; yea, altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther impoſſible, to impoſe our guilt vpon Chriſt and not our ſinne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſinne and guilt goe inſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly together, and where there is no ſinne, there can be no guilt, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that our guilt might be laid vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Chriſt, neceſſarily our ſinne muſt after a ſort be made his, and annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto him, that is, by imputation. Wherefore the more conuenient expoſition, and (as I take it) the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter befitting this place, is, if by ſinne we vnderſtand a grieuous and notorious ſinner, the abſtract em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatically noting the haynouſneſſe of the offence. And indeede the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence muſt needes be great, not which he had committed, but which was imputed vnto him, all the ſinnes
<pb facs="tcp:137:17"/> of the Elect, their periuries, blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, adulteries, murthers, oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Hereſies being laid vpon him, ſo that he might iuſtly be ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and yet without diſgrace vnto his perſon,<note place="margin">Luther. in Gal. <hi>3.13.</hi> &amp; Caluin. idem.</note> 
               <hi>blaſphemus, periurus, hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticorum haereticiſsimus,</hi> (as <hi>Luther</hi> ſpeaketh.)</p>
            <p>Now if any man ſhall reply and ſay theſe are contrary one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for Chriſt to be a ſinner, and to be no ſinner, the anſwere is eaſie: there is no contradiction, vnleſſe the ſame reſpect be obſerued in both, hee is verily a ſinner, and verily no ſinner: in a diuers and ſundry conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, hee is verily no ſinner pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, perſonally, and by act of inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencie; he is a ſinner truely, yet rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely and by act of imputation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For vs.</hi>] That is, ſo many of vs as are elected, and doe beleeue: for we may not thinke that our Sauiour
<pb facs="tcp:137:17"/> Chriſt vndertooke the diſcharge of all mens ſinnes before God, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere and ſatisfie the iuſtice of God for them all; for then why are not all men ſaued? <hi>Col.</hi> 1.14. <hi>In whom we haue redemption by his bloud,</hi> that is, the remiſſion of ſinnes. Out of which place I reaſon thus: All that are effectually redeemed by Chriſt on Gods part, they haue the pardon of their ſins, but all and euery par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ſingular man haue not the pardon of their ſinne, <hi>ergo,</hi> all and euery particular man are not effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually redeemed by Chriſt on Gods part. The propoſition is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt out of the wordes of the text, where redemption and remiſſion of ſinnes, are inſeperably yoaked and coupled together, and reaſon doth enforce the ſame, that where the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of God is fully ſatisfied, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be further obiected vnto,
<pb facs="tcp:137:18"/> or required of the ſinner: &amp; on ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction neceſſarily followeth and de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pendeth the aboliſhment of all ſinne and guilt: for the Aſſumption, that is likewiſe cleere. For if all men had the pardon of their ſins, then ſome who are effectually called, iuſtified, ſanctified and vnited vnto Chriſt, may totally fall away from grace, and finally periſh, which is a helliſh and vncomfortably doctrine; the reprobates may be members of the Catholike Church, which is a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh doctrine: then the gifts and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of God ſhould be ſuch, whereof hee did repent him, if the pardon of ſinne once giuen could be fruſtrate and made void. Wherefore thoſe men that hold and teach that our Sauiour Chriſt tooke vpon him the diſcharge of all mens ſinnes, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe and pacifie the wrath of God for them all, as well of <hi>Caine</hi> as of
<pb facs="tcp:137:18"/> 
               <hi>Abel,</hi> of <hi>Eſau</hi> as of <hi>Iacob,</hi> of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> as of <hi>Moſes,</hi> of <hi>Iudas</hi> as of <hi>Peter,</hi> of reprobate as of elect, they erre and are greatly deceiued, as might be ſhewed at large, if this Text did giue me ſo fit occaſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That we.</hi>] That is, ſo many of vs as doe beleeue. Here comes three things to be expounded: firſt, what this righteouſneſſe here mentioned is: ſecondly, why it is called the righteouſneſſe of God: thirdly, how we become it, and it ours. This righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe that wee may the better conceiue, wee muſt remember this diſtinction. There is in Chriſt a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold righteouſneſſe, according to the diuerſitie of his nature; the one is vncreated and infinite, which is the righteouſneſſe of the Deitie, called by Diuines, his eſſentiall righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: the other is created and finite, which is the righteouſneſſe of the
<pb facs="tcp:137:19"/> humanitie. The former is not here intended or ſpoken of by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, as may appeare by two reaſons: firſt, this righteouſneſſe is infinite, and therefore incommunicable, and if it could be communicated, yet the finite creature were not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of it, conſidering that that which is infinite, can neither be part nor accident of that which is finite: ſecondly, if wee could be capable of it, wee ſhould be Deified; and then the Apoſtle might more ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue ſaid, that wee might be made righteous Gods in him, then the righteouſneſſe of God in him.</p>
            <p>Wherefore the dotage of <hi>Oſian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> concerning the iuſtification of a ſinner by his eſſentiall righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, is to be abhorred and renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced as blaſphemous hereſie, abſurd and ridiculous euen to common ſenſe. As for the place, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4.
<pb facs="tcp:137:19"/> where it is ſaid that the faithfull are made partakers of the diuine nature, it maketh nothing for the patrona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of this errour, for by Nature is not meant ſubſtance, but diuine qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of wiſdome, holines, &amp; righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, liuelily repreſenting the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God, who is wiſdome, holines and righteouſneſſe it ſelfe. The latter is the righteouſnes of the humanity, which is here: which is two-fold, originall, which is the puritie and integritie of his nature, <hi>viz.</hi> the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie of the whole man vnto the will of God: actuall, which is eyther actiue, which he achiued in fulfilling the Law; or paſſiue in his ſufferings. Now this whole righteouſneſſe is imputed vnto vs to iuſtification, as after wee ſhall declare.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place, this righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe is called the righteouſneſſe of God, and that for three cauſes:
<pb facs="tcp:137:20"/> firſt, becauſe God is the ſole Author and giuer of it, Nature doth not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, neither good education, al that free-will &amp; the good vſe of the gifts of Nature doth or can afford is no more but an outward ciuil righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes before men, which cannot iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie a ſinner before God: ſecondly, God alone accepteth it for &amp; in the behalfe of the ſinner, therby giuing him abſolution from guilt, and title and intereſt vnto life: thirdly, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the ſubiect, becauſe it is in that perſon which is not onely man but alſo God, in whom it is reſerued as in a ſtore-houſe for the vſe of the Church.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, this righteouſneſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes ours after this manner; Sinne is that which makes a man vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and the childe of wrath and vengeance: now in ſinne there are three things hurtfull vnto man: the
<pb facs="tcp:137:20"/> firſt is, condemnation or guilt, which is an obligation to puniſhment: the ſecond is actuall diſobedience vnto the morall Law: the third is, origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall corruption, the fountaine of all ſinne: theſe are three deadly wounds and three running ſores in the harts and conſciences of all ſinners.</p>
            <p>Contrariwiſe Chriſt Ieſus is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly righteous, and in him are three ineſtimable benefits, anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the three former euils: firſt, the ſufferings of Chriſt vpon the Croſſe, ſufficient for all mens ſins: ſecondly, the obedience of Chriſt in fulfilling the Law: thirdly, the perfect holineſſe of the humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Chriſt, and theſe are three ſoueraigne medicines to heale all wounded conſciences: and as three running ſtreames of liuing waters to bathe and to ſupple the bruiſed and contrite heart. Now commeth
<pb facs="tcp:137:21"/> Faith, and firſt layeth hold on the ſufferings or paſſiue obedience of Chriſt, which being imputed and appived to the ſinner, hee is deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from guilt and condemnation, and ſo the firſt deadly wound is cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Againe, Faith layeth hold vpon his actiue obedience in fulfilling the Law, which being imputed and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, the perſon of the ſinner is accepted as perfectly iuſt before God, and ſo the ſecond deadly wound is cured Thirdly, Faith ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyeth the holineſſe of his humane nature, called his habituall or origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall righteouſneſſe, whereby hee is accepted of God as perfectly holy, and ſo the third deadly wound is cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. And thus we ſee how this righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe is become ours, and wee it. And thus much ſhall ſuffice to haue ſpoken touching the meaning of the wordes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:137:21"/>
            <p>Now followeth the vſe of doctrine. And to omit many other doctrines which might be gathered out of this place, I will content my ſelfe with this one which the wordes doe naturally afford, being almoſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the Text, to wit, hence we are taught what is the formall cauſe of the iuſtification of a ſinner before God, <hi>viz.</hi> a reciprocall tranſlation of our ſinne vnto Chriſt, and his righteouſneſſe vnto vs, the which comprehendeth the whole forme of Iuſtification: wherein there are two things: firſt, a not imputing of ſin: ſecondly, an imputing of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; for that our ſinnes may not be imputed vnto vs, neceſſarily they muſt be imputed vnto Chriſt; and that we of ſinners may become iuſt, his righteouſneſſe muſt be imputed vnto vs. In a word then, the forme of Iuſtification is the imputation of the
<pb facs="tcp:137:22"/> perfect obedience of Chriſt vnto the beleeuer for the remiſſion of ſinnes, and for righteouſneſſe. This point becauſe it is a fundamentall principle, and a maine ground and piller of our religion, and not a little controuerted betweene the church of Rome and vs, I will ſtand the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in the handling of it, both that we may be confirmed in the truth of ſo neceſſary doctrine, as alſo ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with the armour of proofe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the aſſaults of the aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries wherewith they ſhall impugne it.</p>
            <p>And that wee may proceede in ſome order, wee will conſider theſe three things: firſt, what imputation is: ſecondly, that it is the formall cauſe of the Iuſtification of a ſinner before God: thirdly, we will touch ſome of the principall obiections which are alledged to the contrary
<pb facs="tcp:137:22"/> by that apoſtaticall and hereticall Church of Rome. And to beginne with the name: <hi>Imputation,</hi> is a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphor, borrowed not from num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers &amp; Arithmetique (as ſome haue thought) but from a kinde of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, called acceptilation; wherein the creditor is content to accept the payment of the ſuretie in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of the debter, euen as if hee had diſcharged it in his owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Touching the vſe and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the word, it is two-fold in Scriptures: the firſt is, when an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent qualitie or action procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thence, is imputed vnto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward or puniſhment: for reward, mention is made of it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.4. <hi>to him that worketh, the wages are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted:</hi> an example of it wee haue in <hi>Phinchas, Pſal.</hi> 106.31. whoſe worke the Lord <hi>imputed vnto him for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,</hi> that is, hee approued it,
<pb facs="tcp:137:23"/> accepted it, and rewarded it for the faith of the worker. For puniſhment wee haue an inſtance, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.19. where the varlet <hi>Shimei</hi> doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech <hi>Dauid</hi> on this manner: <hi>Let not my Lord impute wickedneſſe vnto me,</hi> that is, let him not inflict the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of my ſinne vpon mee. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.26. <hi>At my firſt anſwering no man aſsiſted mee, but all forſooke me, I pray God that it may not be laid to their charge.</hi> The ſecond is, when ſomething out of a mans ſelfe is by imputation made his, as though it were inherent in him, or wrought by him: thus it is vſed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.26. <hi>Thy vncircumciſion is made Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion if thou beeſt an obſeruer of the Law.</hi> So to <hi>Philemon,</hi> verſe 18. <hi>If Oneſimus hath done thee any hurt, impute it to me,</hi> or ſet it on my ſcore, <hi>I will repay:</hi> and in this latter ſenſe we are to ſpeake of it in this place.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:137:23"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Imputation</hi> therefore may be thus deſcribed; It is an action of God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting the all-ſufficient and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Obedience of Chriſt, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of the beleeuing ſinner, vnto ſatisfaction and iuſtification. Now then to come to the firſt point, that <hi>Imputation</hi> thus deſcribed, is the forme of the iuſtification of a ſinner before God, though many argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments might be vſed, yet I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent my ſelfe with theſe two, both which are contained in this Text: the former whereof may be framed thus; After what manner Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a ſinner, after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner wee are made iuſt; but hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a ſinner, not by infuſion of any corrupt qualities into his holy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (which were blaſphemie once to conceiue) but by imputation of our ſin onely: therefore we are iuſt before God, not by infuſion of any
<pb facs="tcp:137:24"/> habituall grace into our corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but by imputation of his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe onely. This argument is firme and inuincible, and cannot be deluded, being ſo ſurely grounded vpon this Text If it be replyed (as indeede it is) that if this reaſon of reciprocall imputation be ſo firme, and of ſuch force, why doe not the like conſequents follow of both? to wit, why doth not the imputation of our ſinne vnto Chriſt, as well bring with it inherent corruption in him, as the imputation of his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vnto vs, inherent grace in vs. <hi>Anſ.</hi> The reaſon is farre vnlike; for firſt though ſin be of a very poyſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full nature, yet there is not the like force and power in ſinne to defile and to pollute, as in grace to purge and to ſanctifie, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.15. <hi>The gift is not ſo as is the offence,</hi> noting that there is more vertue and efficacie in
<pb facs="tcp:137:24"/> grace to ſanctifie and to ſaue, then in ſinne to defile and to deſtroy. And indeed Grace is like vnto fire, which though it be for quantitie ſmall, yet for efficacie great: Againe, the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature of Chriſt is ſo repleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with holineſſe, that it is not at all capable of ſinne; but mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is not ſo ſtained and corrupted with ſinne, but that it is capable of grace being at the firſt created after the Image of God, and afterward againe to be re<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ed by Chriſt and therefore conſidering that Chriſt is not ſo capable of ſinne as man is of holines, the reaſon is of no moment. The latter reaſon may be gathered out of the wordes of the Apoſtle, where hee ſaith, <hi>That wee might be made the righteouſnes of God in him:</hi> Whence I reaſon thus: The righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe whereby a ſinner is iuſt before God, is eyther his owne, or
<pb facs="tcp:137:25"/> the righteouſneſſe of another; but it is not his owne, for the Apoſtle would haue ſaid, wee are made the righteouſneſſe of God in our ſelues, and not in him: and thus ſome of the auncient Fathers expounding this place, ſay, that it is not in our ſelues, but in him; not ours, but his: and <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> ſaith, that therfore it is called the righteouſnes of God, becauſe it is without all ſtaine and defect, and therefore cannot poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be inherent in vs, wherefore we may ſafely conclude, that this righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe is not reſident in vs, but receiued from another, and after a ſort made ours, to wit, by imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiect.</hi> But it is excepted, that it is abſurd in reaſon, that a man ſhold be iuſt by the righteouſneſſe of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, euen as if a man ſhould be wiſe by the wiſedome of another, or
<pb facs="tcp:137:25"/> learned by the learning of another, or liue by the life of another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> This reaſon had ſome co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, if the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt were perſonall, and ſo limited and tied vnto him, that it could not from him be deriued vnto others; but it is ſo in him that it may be ours, and conueyed vnto vs by imputation: the reaſon is, becauſe Chriſt is a publike perſon, repreſenting all the Elect; yea, the roote and ſtocke of the Elect, euen as <hi>Adam</hi> was the roote and ſtocke of all mankinde. Looke as therefore the firſt tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of <hi>Adam</hi> was not his alone, but euery particular mans deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from him by generation: euen ſo, the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt is not his alone, but pertaines to all the Elect, being by faith vnited vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and made bone of his bone, and fleſh of his fleſh.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:137:26"/>
            <p>And as the iuyce and ſap which is in the roote of the tree, is made the ſap of the branches by partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation: euen ſo the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt being inherent in him as in the head, is made the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the members by imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And as the Lands and goods of one man are made ouer vnto ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by deed of gift, ſale, exchange, or ſome like conueyance of Law, both for title and vſe: euen ſo, the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, by vertue of the free gift of God, according to the tenure of the Couenant of Grace, is truely and really conuey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto vs and made ours. Theſe two reaſons are ſufficient grounds, whatſoeuer may be excepted to the contrary, whereupon this conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion may be raiſed; that the ſole imputation of the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, is the forme of the iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:137:26"/> of a ſinner before GOD.</p>
            <p>Now followeth the third point, <hi>viz.</hi> the anſwering of thoſe obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which are alledged to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> Firſt of all, it is replyed that <hi>Imputation,</hi> is a conceit inuented and deuiſed by man, not aboue fifty or ſixty yeeres old, not to be found in Scriptures, or in the ancient and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxe Writers of the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To this many things may be anſwered; firſt, what greater im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudencie and bold-hardineſſe can there be, then to contradict the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt and expreſſe teſtimonie of Scripture? for this very <hi>Imputation</hi> is beat vpon and repeated no ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domer then eleuen times in the fourth Chapter to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> and it is as ancient as <hi>Abraham,</hi> of whom it is ſaid, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.6. <hi>He beleeued God and it was imputed vnto him for
<pb facs="tcp:137:27"/> righteouſneſſe:</hi> not as the Papiſts falſely interprete it; that <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith was ſo excellent, that it deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the infuſion of habituall grace, but <hi>Abraham</hi> by faith caſting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and relying vpon the promiſe of grace concerning righteouſneſſe, remiſſion of ſins, and life by Chriſt, was iuſtified, or his Faith was impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto him for righteouſneſſe, <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonimia adiuncti;</hi> that is, what his faith apprehended became his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe by imputation. Againe, it is to be found in the beſt and ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt auncient Writers, <hi>Hierome, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelme,</hi> and <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> vpon this place, who though they doe not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the word <hi>Imputation,</hi> yet vſe it in effect; ſaying, that this righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe is not in vs, but in him, as our ſinne is not his but ours, not in him but in vs, and <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> ſaith, it muſt be without all ſtaine &amp; want.
<pb facs="tcp:137:27"/> So <hi>Aug. in tract.</hi> 3. <hi>in Iohn. &amp; de Sp. &amp; litera, ca.</hi> 9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 26. <hi>&amp; Bernard. ſer.</hi> 62. <hi>in Cant. &amp; ſer. ad milites tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pli, ca.</hi> 11. <hi>mors in Chriſto morte fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatur, &amp; Chriſti iuſtitia nohis impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatur.</hi> Many more teſtimonies might be alledged to this purpoſe, but <hi>qui plura videre cupit, legat</hi> Fulconem <hi>in reſponſione ad annotationes Rhemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſium ſuper hunc locum.</hi> Let then the Rhemiſts mock ſo long as they will, and call this a new no-iuſtice, it is ſufficient for vs, that it is grounded on Scriptures, and wanteth not the teſtimonie of the Church.</p>
            <p>To proceede further, <hi>Imputation</hi> is not a meere deuice, but a very thing; for it is a relation, that is, an ordination, or application of that which the Logitians call the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vnto his terme, or of the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue vnto his correlatiue, for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: In <hi>Imputation</hi> the fundament is
<pb facs="tcp:137:28"/> the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt; the terme is the perſon of the beleeuer; and the relation is the mercy of God, or the action of God merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accepting the perfect righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſt in the behalfe of the beleeuer. Now this is not a fiction: and if a relation be nothing, how ſhall wee diſtinguiſh the perſons in Trinitie, who though they ſubſiſt all in one infinite, &amp; vndiuided eſſence, yet are three really diſtinguiſhed by an inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municable propertie, which is nothing elſe but a relation? Again, if a relation be nothing, what ſhall be the internall forme of a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? is it any other but a relation or proportion betweene the ſigne and the thing ſignified? And if a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation be nothing, many a man is vniuſtly adiudged and condemned to dye, both in the Courts of men, and in the court of Conſcience, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:137:28"/> God: for why doe men daily dye the death of the body, and the death of the ſoule, is it not becauſe they are guiltie? And if ſin had not guiltineſſe annexed vnto it as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable propertie thereof, men might at their pleaſures breake and tranſgreſſe both the Lawes of God and of men, and neuer be obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to puniſhment: for it is not ſin, but guilt that bindes ouer vnto pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment: now what elſe is this guilt but a relation? and if the imputation of <hi>Adams</hi> ſin vnto vs be ſomething, why ſhould not the imputation of Chriſts righteouſneſſe be alſo ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and not a meere figment as they would make it? Nay, Relations (as the Schoole-men ſpeak, though they be <hi>minimae entitatis,</hi> yet are they <hi>maximae efficaciae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude this point, behold what iniurie this Antichriſtian Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue
<pb facs="tcp:137:29"/> doth offer vnto our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt: the Pope forſooth, by vertue of the keyes, hath power to diſpenſe and apply the merits of one man to another, inſomuch as all his Indulgences are imputatiue, but Chriſt hath not this power. What is this elſe, but to deny vnto the Head, that which they allow vnto the members? and to giue to their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteriall head, that which they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie vnto the imperiall, as they foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly diſtinguiſh? But not content with this, they pleade further for themſelues, ſaying, that there is no neceſſitie of the imputation of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, becauſe wee are iuſtified by an inherent righteouſneſſe, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from Chriſt by infuſion: this they labour to confirme by teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of Scripture, principally out of <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.18. <hi>As by the offence of one man many dye;</hi> out of which place
<pb facs="tcp:137:29"/> they reaſon thus: As the imputatiue diſobedience of <hi>Adam</hi> did <hi>truly</hi> print into the nature of man, corruption and ſinne, and not putatiuely onely, as they ſpeake: ſo the imputatiue obedience of Chriſt, doth print into the nature of man holineſſe &amp; grace, and notiby imputation onely. This argument they take to be ſo firme and ſo ſtrong that it admitteth no anſwere, which notwithſtanding, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well weighed is of no moment: for if all were graunted, nothing could be proued, vnleſſe it could be ſhewed that this righteouſnes prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in our natures, and reſident in vs, were that whereby a ſinner is iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified before God, which cannot be, as is manifeſt by this reaſon: That righteouſneſſe which muſt abſolue and acquite a ſinner before God, muſt be abſolute and perfect, and in all points anſwerable and corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent
<pb facs="tcp:137:30"/> vnto the rigour and extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of the morall Law; but our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent righteouſneſſe is not ſuch, nay,<note place="margin">Pſal. 143.2 Dan. 9.18.</note> it is imperfect in this life, and therfore <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Daniel</hi> durſt not oppoſe it to the ſeuere examination of gods iudgement ſeat, but renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced it, and relyed themſelues onely vpon the meer mercy of God, &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt, and ſo haue the Saints of God done from time to time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. Though he had a great meaſure of this inherent righteouſneſſe, yet teſtifieth plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that hee is not thereby iuſtified; and S. <hi>Iohn</hi> telleth vs,<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.11</note> that it is min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled and blemiſhed with ſinne in this life; and if any man think other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, he is no better then a lyar and an hypocrite. But let all be granted which this place in ſhew of wordes, and according to their interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, will or can afford, it ſerueth as
<pb facs="tcp:137:30"/> much to ſtabliſh iuſtification by imputation, as by inherencie; yea, and more rather, by how much the cauſe is of greater force then the effect: for as the imputatiue ſinne of <hi>Adam</hi> was the cauſe of inherent corruption in mans nature; euen ſo the imputatiue righteouſneſſe of Chriſt is the cauſe of inherent grace in the faithfull. And now to take this weapon out of their hands, which they haue drawne (as it were) to cut the throate of <hi>Imputation,</hi> it may fitly be retorted vpon their owne heads on this manner: As the imputatiue diſobedience of <hi>Adam</hi> was ſufficient to make all men guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and culpable of condemnation before God, though it left behinde it no print or impreſſion of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the nature of man: euen ſo, the imputatiue righteouſneſſe of Chriſt is ſufficient to diſcharge and
<pb facs="tcp:137:31"/> abſolue vs of this guilt, though it ſhould bring with it no inherent righteouſneſſe in vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> Further, they reaſon for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues out of <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.24. the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of the Meſſias is an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall righteouſneſſe, but this impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiue righteouſneſſe ceaſeth at the end of this life: <hi>ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Though the act of imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of righteouſneſſe ceaſeth after death, becauſe there is no remiſſion of ſins this life ended, yet the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe imputed abideth ſtill, and ſtandeth a man in ſtead to diſcharge and ſet him free from all the ſins of his life by-paſt, which otherwiſe the Lord might require at his hands. Againe, it remaineth in an inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable fruit and effect of it, which is perfect holineſſe, to wit, a confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of the whole man vnto the will of God.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:137:31"/>
            <p>Thus being deſtitute of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, they flye vnto reaſon, plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for themſelues in this manner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiect.</hi> Chriſt, the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> did reſtore no more then the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> loſt; but the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> neuer had, and therefore could neuer loſe this imputatiue righteouſneſſe: <hi>ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The propoſition is falſe; for Chriſt, as hee was euery way farre more excellent then <hi>Adam</hi> was, ſo he is far more liberall in conferring grace, and in beſtowing his gifts, then <hi>Adam</hi> was prodigall in loſing them, and in depriuing himſelfe and his poſteritie of them, and therfore vouchſafed many more and greater gifts vnto vs, then <hi>Adam</hi> euer loſt: for firſt, <hi>Adam</hi> neuer had iuſtifying Faith, neyther indeede was it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary in that eſtate: hee beleeued in God, but hee knew not, neyther beleeued in the Meſſias; but Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:137:32"/> hath vouchſafed vs this ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall gift of iuſtifying Faith. Againe, <hi>Adam</hi> had not the grace of confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and finall perſeuerance, and therfore being tempted, ſell though the free motion of his owne will: but wee haue the ſecond grace, that is, of corroboration, whereby wee are preſerued in the ſtate of grace, which is the priuiledge of the ſtate of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, before the ſtate of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie. <hi>Adam</hi> had power to haue ſtood, if hee would, but hee had no power to will that hee could, but we by the bleſſing of God haue in ſome part, both the <hi>poſſe</hi> and the <hi>velle,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as it is not poſſible for vs, being once in the ſtate of grace, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther totally to fall, or finally to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. For the Aſſumption: <hi>Adam</hi> had the ſame righteouſnes for ſubſtance which we haue, but not in one and the ſame manner: <hi>Adam</hi> had it reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb facs="tcp:137:32"/> in his perſon by inherencie, but wee haue it out of our ſelues from another by imputation.</p>
            <p>Now being deſtitute both of Scriptures and reaſon, they try ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, if not to ſtabliſh their own ſuppoſed righteouſnes, yet to bring our doctrine of imputation in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to contempt, and therefore they ſearch their wits, labouring by all meanes to faſten ſome groſſe abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities vpon it, but all in vaine. Firſt therefore, they reaſon thus: If the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt be the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of a ſinner, then euery ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that beleeueth is as righteous as Chriſt, and conſequently a Sauiour; both which are abſurd: the ground of this argument is, becauſe the ſelfe-ſame perfect righteouſneſſe, which is in Chriſt, both for parts and degrees, is made his by impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, the which is neceſſary, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:137:33"/> the righteouſneſſe which iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth muſt be abſolute, and in all points anſwerable vnto the morall Law. For the anſwering of this, firſt, conſider the abſurditie of this kinde of reaſoning in the like inſtances: If the light of the Sunne be the light of the Ayre, then the Ayre is as lightſome as the Sunne, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the Sunne it ſelfe, that is, the fountaine of light and heate. If the heate of the fire be the heate of a mans hand, then the hand is as hot as the fire. If the water of the fountaine be the water of the riuer, then the riuer is the fountaine, or as copious and cleere as the fountaine. Who can endure to heare this idle and fooliſh talking, for it deſerueth not the name of reaſoning? nay, whoſe eares doe not glow to heare it? But to ſatisfie this cauill and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtication more fully, both the
<pb facs="tcp:137:33"/> conſequents of the Propoſition are falſe. For firſt, though the ſame righteouſneſſe which is in Chriſt be made ours, yet not in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: in him it is inherent, as in his proper ſubiect; in vs it is not reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, but after a ſort annexed vnto vs, to wit, by imputation: Againe, though it were in vs as it is in him, yet it ſhould not be equall in both.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiect.</hi> But it will be ſaid, it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like perfect in both, therefore equall in both.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It followeth not; for the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of inequalitie ariſeth not of the righteouſneſſe it ſelfe, which of it ſelfe, and by it ſelfe conſidered, neyther admitteth decreaſe nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe; but from the diuerſitie of the ſubiect: for being in Chriſt, it is not the righteouſnes of a bare crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but of him alſo that is the Creator; yea, of God himſelfe, for
<pb facs="tcp:137:34"/> whom Chriſt ſuffered, God ſuffered; when Chriſt obeyed, God obeyed, inſomuch as this righteouſneſſe is of infinite merit, price, value and dignitie, to ſatisfie for the whole world; yea, of ten thouſand worlds, if it were therto appointed by God: but in man it is the righteouſneſſe of a bare creature, and no more: the diuerſitie therefore of the ſubiect doth adde great excellencie vnto it, though the thing for ſubſtance be the ſame in both.</p>
            <p>To explane this by this compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: The ſame righteouſneſſe which is in Chriſt, is in the good Angell, and as perfect both for ſubſtance and degree, ſhall wee therefore rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that the good Angell is as righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous as Chriſt? nothing leſſe: and why? becauſe the righteouſneſſe of the one is but the righteouſneſſe of the creature, the other is beſides, the
<pb facs="tcp:137:34"/> righteouſneſſe of the Creator. The other conſequent is farre more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, for though the infinite merit of Chriſt be imputed to the ſinner, yet not infinitely, but ſo farre forth as it ſerueth to ſatisfie the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of God, and to make him righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous before God.</p>
            <p>To make this plaine by a familiar compariſon: The whole light of the Sunne is communicated to one ſtar, yet not wholy, but with a <hi>quatenus,</hi> ſo farre forth as it cauſeth the ſaid Starre to ſhine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiect.</hi> Further, they would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre a ſecond abſurditie: If we be righteous by the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt imputed, then hee is a ſinner by the imputation of our ſinne, and conſequently the childe of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, which is blaſphemie once to remember.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> We may ſafely and without
<pb facs="tcp:137:35"/> indignitie vnto the holy perſon of our Sauiour Chriſt, &amp; according to the tenure of this Scripture, terme him a ſinner, yet not properly, but relatiuely only, as we ſhewed before: neither doth it hence follow that he is become the childe of the Diuell, for a man may be properly and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally a ſinner, and yet not the childe of the Diuell; much more then imputatiuely: but this diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall title, Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> giueth onely to thoſe that commit ſin, that is, wholy addict themſelues to the practiſe of ſinne, with full conſent of will, and with delight, and make an Art and occupation of ſinning, and keepe a courſe therein: for the children of God, though they be ſinfull, yet they are not the Sonnes of the Diuell, but the adopted Sonnes and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiect.</hi> But it will be ſaid, that
<pb facs="tcp:137:35"/> Chriſt in vs is become a committer of ſinne, becauſe our commiſſions are imputed vnto him; why may not he therefore be termed <hi>filius diaboli,</hi> at the leaſt by imputation?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To this I anſwere: howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer our ſinne is in regard of the guilt and puniſhment tranſlated vnto Chriſt, yet no further, and therfore theſe conſequents of <hi>filius irae,</hi> which agreeth onely to them that are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of <hi>Adams</hi> ſinnes, and <hi>filius di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aboli,</hi> which agreeth onely to them that perſonally worke and practiſe ſinne, cannot be extended to him who is onely relatiuely a ſinner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiect.</hi> If wee by this righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe imputed, be made <hi>filij Dei,</hi> then why ſhould not hee by imputation of our ſinnes be made <hi>filius Diaboli?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The reaſon is not alike, he is not at all capable of the one, but we are capable of the other: neither
<pb facs="tcp:137:36"/> is it neceſſary that euery conſequent and property of ſinne, which it hath and bringeth with it in vs, ſhould be tranſlated vnto Chriſt: for it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be proued by Scripture that he tooke any more vpon him then the guilt, fault, and puniſhment of our ſinnes.</p>
            <p>To make this plaine by compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: The debt of one man is impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto another, <hi>viz.</hi> the Suretie, and yet not the conſequent of the debt, for the debt in the debter hath banqueruptneſſe annexed vnto it, which it hath not in the ſurety, being an able man: ſo our ſinnes in vs haue many titles and conſequents annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto them, mentioned in the Scripture, which cannot be faſtned vpon Chriſt, and it were great iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to impute them vnto him, as it is great iniquitie for the debter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides his debt to impute alſo his
<pb facs="tcp:137:36"/> banqueruptnes vnto the ſurety: nay, if the debter ſhal but call his pledge, or terme him a banquerupt imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely, in regard of his proper debt tranſlated vnto the other, hee ſhall offer him no ſmall iniurie and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, and teſtifie his vnthankefull minde: how much leſſe may this vile title either imputatiuely or falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be aſcribed vnto Chriſt, without great diſgrace and diſhonour to his perſon? inaſmuch as that onely the Scripture teſtifieth to be imputed vnto him, which falleth vnder ſinne, <hi>viz.</hi> fault, guilt, puniſhment, and not all that followeth vpon it in vs.</p>
            <p>But how then is that title taken from vs? doe we ſtill after iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion remaine the ſonnes of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell? nothing leſſe: for wee are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the adopted Sonnes of God in Chriſt. Now that which giueth vs the right of adoption doth abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh
<pb facs="tcp:137:37"/> the former title, which is not the imputation of this diabolicall title from vs vnto Chriſt, but the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Chriſts righteouſneſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, whereby wee are become no ſonnes of the Diuell, but Sonnes of God.</p>
            <p>And to conclude, this very blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, which they doe ſo much feare and abhorre, may (will they, nill they) be faſtned vpon their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Iuſtification: for if wee be iuſtified by the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt infuſed, then hee is a ſinner by our ſinne and corruption infuſed, and ſo ſhall become indeede <hi>filius diaboli,</hi> or elſe the Apoſtles Antithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis fals to the ground, which to the iudgement of any indifferent man is firme and ſure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> It is further replyed that vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this doctrine of Imputation it will follow, that God ſhal pronounce
<pb facs="tcp:137:37"/> a falſe iudgement, <hi>viz.</hi> him to be iuſt, who is indeede vniuſt, and a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, euen as if a man ſhould ſalue vp a wound, and draw ouer a skin ouer that which is feſtered and corrupted within: or as if one ſhould build a Tombe, paint it, and make it glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous without, there being nothing within but rottenneſſe, ſtinke, and dead mens bones.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The conſequent alſo is falſe, for God doth pronounce no man iuſt, whom he doth not make iuſt at the very ſame inſtant, euen in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: for by the ſelfe-ſame act wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a man is iuſtified, hee is alſo ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, and by the ſame iuſtice and no other; for that which is imputed to iuſtifie, is alſo infuſed to ſanctifie, and is inherent in vs, at the leaſt, in the fruit and efficacie of it. To ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plane this further; the perſon who is iuſtified, ceaſeth to be a ſinner in
<pb facs="tcp:137:38"/> regard of guilt wholy, and in regard of the corruption of nature alſo in part, which though it be not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together aboliſhed, yet it receiueth a deadly wound in the very act and inſtant, and neuer raigneth after; yea, to proceede further, at the very ſame time, and in the ſame act, hee is preſently ſanctified, and therfore worthily eſteemed and adiudged of God, holy and iuſt preſently, I ſay, in regard of all the parts and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of holineſſe, which is after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to receiue his accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by degrees in this life, and in death, to be wholy conſummate and finiſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> Laſtly, they vrge and ſay, that it cannot ſtand with Gods iuſtice, to iuſtifie and abſolue a ſinner: for <hi>Prou.</hi> 17.15. <hi>To iuſtifie the wicked, and to condemne the iuſt, both theſe are abhominable to the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:137:38"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Indeed to iuſtifie the wicked perſon, and to acquite him in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without all manner of ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction made eyther by himſelfe or ſome other, were iniuſtice. But God which iuſtifieth the vngodly, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5. doth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite and abſolue them for the all-ſufficient ſatisfaction of Chriſt, and they though they be wicked and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly before their iuſtification, yet in it, and by it, they become righteous both before God, and alſo in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in part. (<g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>)</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:137:39"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:137:39"/>
            <head>A right godly Prayer, made by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Newhouſe,</hi> to be ſaid either Morning or Euening, as accaſion ſhall ſerue, changing ſome few words. (<g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>)</head>
            <p>MOſt mercifull and louing father in Ieſus Chriſt, we beſeech thee to remoue all impediments which vſually hinder vs in this exerciſe of prayer, &amp; quicken vp our hearts with feare and reuerence of thy Maieſtie, in feeling of our owne wants, in a deſire to receiue a ſupply of them from thee, and in aſſurance to be heard of thee in all our ſuites and requeſts, to put vp our praiers and ſupplications vnto thee.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord our God, wee doe here in thy preſence ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge and confeſſe that we are of our ſelues moſt wretched and miſerable ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,
<pb facs="tcp:137:40"/> both in reſpect of the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our hearts, as alſo the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions of our liues: more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly we doe acknowledge the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelitie of our hearts, whereby wee haue not yet learned to depend vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy prouidence for the things of this life, nor vpon thy mercy, for the ſaluation of our ſoules: hence comes impatience vnder the croſſe, diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentation with our preſent eſtate, doubting and diſtruſtfulnes in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of our ſaluation, immoderate care and deſire of the things of this life: we confeſſe alſo the Atheiſme and profanes both of our mindes and harts, whereby all our thoughts and affections are eſtranged from thee, and ſo glued &amp; faſtened to the things of this world, that wee can take more ioy and delight in doing our owne wills, and in ſeruing our owne luſts, then euer we would doe
<pb facs="tcp:137:40"/> in ſeruing and obaying thee; we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge likewiſe the pride of our harts, whereby wee doe exalt our ſelues in the vanitie of our owne conceits againſt thy Maieſtie, and aboue our brethren, whom thou haſt made far more excellent then our ſelues: our ſecurity of the fleſh, whereby wee put away the day of euill and wrath farre from vs, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing vnto our ſelues immunitie from all thy curſes and plagues, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding wee walke in ſinne and in the ſtubbornes of our harts: our vaine-glory, whereby wee deſire praiſe and commendation among men, more then thy glory; our ſelfe-loue, whereby wee loue our owne eaſe, libertie, peace, carnall pleaſures more then thy Maieſtie, more then our brethren: our hipocriſie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee content our ſelues with an outward name and profeſſion of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
<pb facs="tcp:137:41"/> and holines before men, not regarding the truth and power of godlines: anſwerably our liues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in all actuall tranſgreſſions againſt euerie one of thy commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements: we haue liued in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of thy prouidence, and haue not beene aſhamed to commit ſinne and wickednes in thy ſight: in the abuſe of thy mercies, and haue not beene drawen neerer vnto thee: in the neglect of thy iudgments, and fatherlie chaſticements, partly vpon others, and partlie vpon our ſelues, and haue not profitted thereby to true repentance and reformation of life: in the profanation of all thy holy ordinances, thy Word, Sacraments, this exerciſe of Prayer, neither pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring our ſelues hereunto aright, nor being conuerſant therein with that care, diligence, &amp; conſcience, as we ought, and therefore haue miſſed
<pb facs="tcp:137:41"/> of that fruit of edification we might haue reaped by the reuerent and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious handling of theſe thy diuine ordinances, in the abuſe of thy crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures vnto intemperancy and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, whereby we haue diſabled our ſelues to thy worſhip and ſeruice, &amp; to the duties of our particular cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings. Many other ſinnes haue wee committed, the leaſt whereof if thou ſhouldeſt lay vnto our charge, wee were neuer able to appeare in thy preſence or to anſwer thee one of a thouſand: wee beſeech thee to deale fauourably with vs, as thou art wont to doe with thy children, that call vpon thy name and ſeeke thee in the truth of their harts, and in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of iudgement, remember mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie; open our blind eyes, that we may come to a particular knowledge of our owne ſinnes; touch our hard and ſtonie harts that wee may ſigh and
<pb facs="tcp:137:42"/> grone vnder the burden of them, being heartily diſpleaſed with our ſelues, becauſe therein we haue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured thy name. Stirre vp our hearts alſo, that wee may hunger and thirſt after Chriſt and his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and after euery drop of his moſt precious bloud: in him alone be well pleaſed with vs, and for his merit and righteouſneſſe vouchſafe mercifully and freely to doe away all our offences: waſh them all away in the precious bloud of Ieſus Chriſt, and our hearts from the filthineſſe and impuritie of them all. Say vnto our ſoules, thou art our ſaluation: let thy holy and good ſpirit of Adoption, cry in our hearts through Ieſus Chriſt <hi>Abba-Father,</hi> telling and perſwading vnto our conſciences by the inward teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of the ſame Spirit, that our ſins are pardoned, and we ſtand diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb facs="tcp:137:42"/> of them all before thy tribunall ſeate.</p>
            <p>And becauſe our faith is weake, partly through the manifold cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions that be in our hearts, and partly through the innumerable tranſgreſſions that breake out into our liues, we beſeech thee to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the ſame by the often conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, meditation, and application of thy mercifull promiſes made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs in Chriſt, ſtirring vp our vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing hearts to aſſent vnto, and to apply the ſame, that wee may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue comfort thereby, ſpecially in the time of danger and diſtreſſe; and namely, in the agonie of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and in the houre of death. And becauſe there can be no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter enemie to true Faith, then is carnall confidence and vaine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, confound this helliſh and damnable corruption in euery one
<pb facs="tcp:137:43"/> of our harts, and worke in the ſame the contrary grace of thy holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, namely, true Humilitie, whereby wee may acknowledge our owne no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and may vtterly renounce and deny ourſelues, and learne one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and wholy to relye and depend vpon the bleſſed merit of Chriſt, in matter of our ſaluation, aſcribing the whole worke and glory thereof to him alone, and to no other thing.</p>
            <p>And becauſe all that are in Chriſt are new creatures, and walke not according to the fleſh, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſpirit, wee beſeech thee to renue vs in the ſpirits of our mindes, and in the affections of our hearts, enlightening vs more and more with true knowledge and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding in ſpirituall things, and ſanctifying our hearts to the loue and obedience thereof, that wee may walke worthy of thee, pleaſe
<pb facs="tcp:137:43"/> thee in all things, fructifie in euery good worke, and increaſe in the knowledge of thy holy will. Aboue all things ſet before vs thy holy feare, imprint this grace of thine deepely in our hearts, perſwade vs effectually of thy preſence where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer we doe become, in ſecret or open place, that wee may learne to make conſcience of ſinne, and of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery euill way, endeuoring to pleaſe and obey thee in all thy Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, and euermore to preſerue pure and vnblameable conſciences before thee and before all men, and that to the end of our dayes.</p>
            <p>And becauſe wee are at continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all warre againſt Sathan, this wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked world, and our owne damnable and fleſhly luſts, Lord help vs in this ſpirituall combate, in all temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; when wee are moſt weake, be thou moſt ſtrong in vs, together with
<pb facs="tcp:137:44"/> the temptation, grant an iſſue and an euaſion: teach vs to watch ouer our owne hearts, and to keepe them with all diligent obſeruation, that wee be not any more circumuented of the wiles of Sathan, or ſeduced through the deceitfulneſſe of ſinne. Help our infirmities, giue ſtrength againſt our particular corruptions, that in the very act of temptation, wee may be able to reſiſt and to ouercome, that wee may haue as iuſt cauſe to praiſe thy name in our victories, as wee haue had cauſe to be humbled and caſt downe in our foyles.</p>
            <p>And becauſe it is the lot of thy Children in this world, to be tryed ſundry wayes; Lord prepare vs to the dayes of tryall, arme vs with ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall patience to beare thy hand, that wee may meekely and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly ſubmit our wils to thy good
<pb facs="tcp:137:44"/> will and pleaſure; howſoeuer it ſhall pleaſe thee to deale with vs, onely teach vs to profit vnder thy rods of correction: grant that we may learne hereby, to deny our ſelues, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake this world, pleaſures, profits, &amp; preferments of it; to make vile and baſe account of them in reſpect of heauenly things, to loue thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and thy righteouſneſſe, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to be diſſolued and to be with Chriſt, that ſinne and the corruption thereof might be aboliſhed, and we might haue neere coniunction with thy Maieſtie in thine owne king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Neuertheleſſe, ſo long as thou pleaſeſt to hold vs here in this earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tabernacle, diſſolue in our hearts the curſed workes of the Diuell, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the power and tyranny of ſin daily more and more; increaſe the Graces of thy holy Spirit, namely, Faith and repentance, thy feare and
<pb facs="tcp:137:45"/> thy loue, humilitie, and a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, with all other graces wherby thy own image may be renued in vs daily, that the longer we liue in this world, the nearer we may draw to thy Kingdome, the greater ſtrength we may haue againſt our owne ſins, the greater will and abilitie to ſerue and pleaſe thee in righteouſneſſe and new obedience.</p>
            <p>Bleſſe with vs thy whole Church and euery member thereof: be good and gratious to theſe Churches in England and Ireland: giue thy Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell a free paſſage euery where, with all good meanes whereby it may be further publiſhed and maintained, remouing all lets and impediments wherby the courſe and proceedings thereof are hindered and ſtayed: for this cauſe be good vnto our graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous King, the principall member therof: bleſſe him with life &amp; honor,
<pb facs="tcp:137:45"/> confirme his heart in the truth of this holy Religion hee hath a long time profeſſed, and maintained, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the aduerſaries thereof, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing his loue and zeale thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and his conſtancie therein, and adding vnto his yeeres many dayes, that he may be an ancient Father in this Church of thine, a Patron &amp; an vpholder of thy pure and true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, againſt all them that oppoſe themſelues againſt it. Bleſſe our gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Queene, the Prince, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue of that Royall Progenie. Be mercifull to the Honourable Priuie Counſell, and the inferiour Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of this Land, bleſſing them with the wiſedome of thy ſpirit from aboue, that they may take counſell with thy word in all their enterpriſes and deliberations, ſo as firſt they may conclude of thoſe things which make moſt for the aduancement of
<pb facs="tcp:137:46"/> thy Kingdome and Goſpell; and then for the peaceable and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous gouernment both of Church and Common-weale. Bleſſe the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of thy word and Sacraments: increaſe the number of thoſe that are faithfull and painefull; double thy ſpirit and graces vpon them, that they may goe in and out before thy people, not onely in the light of pure doctrine, but of holy and vnblame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able conuerſation, that by this meanes many may be wonne to the knowledge and obedience of thy truth. Be mercifull to the people of this Land: confirme them that are called; and ſtrengthen them that they may continue ſtedfaſt in the ſinceere profeſſion and practiſe of true religion vnto the end: thoſe that yet wander and goe aſtray through ſinne and wickedneſſe; call them home in thy owne good time,
<pb facs="tcp:137:46"/> that they with vs, and we with them, may haue both hearts and mouthes enlarged to glorifie thy holy name. Touch all our hearts with true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance from the higheſt to the loweſt, that thy iudgements preſent and imminent may be remoued &amp; preuented, thy mercies ſtill procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto vs, and the poſteritie after vs, eſpecially in the continuance of thy word and Goſpell among vs for euer.</p>
            <p>Lord be mercifull to all thine af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, whether they be ſicke vpon their beds, or diſtreſſed in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for ſinne, or perſecuted for thy name and truth, or pinched with pouerty, wanting thoſe outward things which thou haſt in great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance delt out vnto vs, relieue them according to their ſeuerall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, ſtrengthen them in their weakneſſe, comfort them in their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:137:47"/> mitigate their ſorrowes and extremities, put an end vnto them in thine owne good time, and turne them to their humiliation, and in the end, to their eternall comfort and ſaluation by Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Be mercifull to our friends in the fleſh, and acquaintance in the ſpirit, parents, brethren, ſiſters, children, ſeruants, and all other, for whom we are bound by any dutie to pray, granting vnto them a ſupply of all graces needfull for their preſent ſtate and calling, and the finall ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their ſoules. Haue mercie on vs, now calling on thy name; forgiue our ſinnes and manifold defects in this holy dutie, and accept at our hands this weake and imperfect obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in Chriſt: and giue vs thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hearts for all mercies receiued from thy bountifull hand, that thou haſt loued vs in Ieſus Chriſt with an
<pb facs="tcp:137:47"/> euerlaſting loue before the world was, and from loue haſt choſen vs to life and glory; called vs in time, to the certaine knowledge of this our Election; iuſtified and redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vs by Ieſus Chriſt his death and reſurrection; ſanctified vs in the inner man by his holy ſpirit; that thou haſt giuen vs Faith in thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and hope of a better life, feare of thy Name, loue of thy Maieſtie, zeale of thy glory, loue and tender affection towards our brethren; yea, towards our enemies, and thoſe that hate vs; patience vnder the Croſſe, ſtrength againſt our particular temptations and corruptious; Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, gentleneſſe, &amp; meeknes, with many other gifts and graces of rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, all which we acknowledge haue proceeded of thy meere mercy and goodneſſe towards vs, wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee to increaſe them daily
<pb facs="tcp:137:48"/> more and more in vs, and <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et vs not be negligent in the vſe of all good meanes, whereby they may grow in vs daily. We doe alſo with all thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, remember all temporall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings concerning this life, and the preſeruation thereof, our health, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, peace, proſperitie, and all outward things wee doe enioy, this gratious gouernment, with all bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings accompanying the ſame. We thanke thee, that thou haſt ſuſtained vs in great weakeneſſe, relieued vs in much neceſſitie, comforted vs in much diſtreſſe, reſolued vs in many doubts, deliuered vs from many and great dangers, and when wee were falling into them, haſt reſcued vs with thine owne hand, and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vs from many grieuous ſinnes, into which through the corruptions of our natures and Sathans temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, wee might haue fallen.
<pb facs="tcp:137:48"/> Make vs <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nfaignedly thankfull, and teach vs to walke worthy of them, and to teſtifie thankfulnes therefore, not in word onely, but by a conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable walking with thee in all duty and obedience vnto the end.</p>
            <p>Bleſſe vs this night, keepe vs and all ours from all dangers, grant vnto vs (if it be thy holy and good will) ſuch a portion of reſt and ſleepe, that thereby body and ſenſes being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed, we may riſe vp in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning cheerfully, to glorifie thy name in the duties of Chriſtianitie, and in the works of our particular callings, as thou ſhalt ſeuerally diſpoſe of vs, and giue vs ſtrength and opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and that by Ieſus Chriſt In whoſe name we conclude our prayers as he himſelfe hath taught vs, ſaying, <hi>Our Father which art, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
